Guide to the Ruth Porter Ward personal papers, 1909-1965 COR0010.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ruth Porter Ward personal papers
1909-1965
1923-1936
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ward, Ruth Porter
COR0010.MS
1 Linear Feet 1 slim document box and 1 flat box
Ruth Porter Ward (1900 September 16 - 1936 July 24) was an artist primarily known for her still lifes and portraits done with oil, pastel, and watercolor. Ward was a student at the Corcoran School of art from 1920 through 1928. This collection contains newspaper articles, correspondence, postcards, art work and photographs related to the artist life of Ruth Porter Ward. The bulk dates of the collection materials is from 1923 through 1965 although there is artwork from when Ward was a child.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains newspaper articles, correspondence, postcards, artwork and photographs related to the artist life of Ruth Porter Ward. The bulk dates of the collection materials is from 1923 through 1965 although there is artwork that Ward created as a child. Much of the newpaper articles concerns art competitions and prizes both about Ward, but more generally about many local DC artists. The correspondence includes Ward interacting with people who commissioned her to paint portraits or purchased her non-commmissioned works. The correspondence also includes a small bound notebook with letters of support for Ward as an applicant with the Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation. There are also two short notes from Cuthbert Powell Minnigerode, Director of the Corcoran, hoping Ward gets better from her illness. The photographs include images of Ward and friends as well as her art work and the subjects of her portrraits. The artwork includes oil paintings, pencil, crayon, and charcoal. The are also several certificate of awards from the Corcoran.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Personal papers and Artwork
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Porter Ward (1900 September 16 - 1936 July 24) was an artist known for her still lifes and portraits in oil, pastel, and watercolor. She attended the Corcoran School of Art from October 1920 through 1928. She painted many portraits on commission and exhibited much of her non-commissioned work throughout the District. She also spent a year working and volunteering with the Red Cross where she created campaign posters. Ward was a member of both the Washington Society of Artists and the Washington Water Color Club. She was awarded the prize for still-life study at the annual exhibit of the Society of Washington Artists at the Corcoran Art Gallery in 1932.
Ruth Porter Ward was born in Statesville, North Corolina on September 16 1900. She was injured in a fall at the age of three and used crutches to assist her walking until the age of fifteen. Ward's family moved to Alexandria Virginia in 1917. Ward spent some time as a student at the National School of Fine and Applied Arts before attended the Corcoran. Her career was just beginning to flourish when she died in July 1936.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Corcoran Institution Board of Trustees donated these records to The George Washington University in 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Corcoran Gallery of Art; Ward, Ruth Porter
- Personal papers, 1923-1965; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains newspaper articles, correspondence, postcards, and photographs related to the work of artist Ruth Porter Ward. The materials date from 1923-1965.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by folder titles. Most folder titles were derived by staff based on the type of materials found in the folders, but the folders were all maintained as received.
  - Award certificates, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    General
    To Ruth Porter Ward. Two awards from the Corcoran School of Art. One award for $25 for the 1922-1923 Still Life class and another $15 for the Still Life class 1923-1924.
  - Correspondence, 1923-1965; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Images of Ward's paintings, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, postcards, and correspondence, 1923-1965; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This folder is divided into groups by the names of Ward's contemporaries including Corcoran faculty and artist friends. A handwritten list is provided at the front of the folder.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1935-1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1928-1932; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1923-1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Artwork, 1909 and undated; Series 2
  This series contains artwork mostly created by Ruth Porter Ward. The media include painting, oil and water color as well as pencil, ink and crayon drawings. Most are not dated, but there is one booklet that is dated 1909.
  Arranged in no particular order
  - Artwork: pencil, crayon, paint, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artwork: booklet titled Flowers of Spring, 1909; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Artwork: pencil drawing, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Artwork: crayon, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Artwork: lithograph, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Artwork: ink on paper, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Artwork: painting, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Artwork: charcoal, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Artwork: pencil, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Poster, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - book: The Art of Japanese Brush Paintings by Jack McDowell and Takahiko Mikami, 1961; Series 2 (Box 2, Item 1)